could you tell a little bit about the
very beginnings of the new alchemy
Institute oh it all started uh well it
was right about the time of well 1917
just before when people were just there
was a new wave of environmental
awareness Paul Ehrlich had published the
Population Bomb there was a lot of
people beginning to talk about the
environment and read about the
environment and we were living in San
Diego in California and John and his
colleague Villa Carney and others were
starting to listen to what people were
saying and we became concerned and
thought we got to learn more so we start
to hold some evening seminars in our
living room we talked for a long time
about all of us going wrong you know
then from car exhausts in the air
supposing to cause brain damage damage
and children nitrate from fertilizers
leaching into the ground and also
affecting the health of children through
groundwater and we got tired of just
what John a bill called doom watching
documenting everything that was going
wrong and start to ask ourselves can we
do anything about it and I became clear
to us that we didn't know whether we
could create change but we thought we
should try so we started welcoming with
the question it's impossible for the
present human population to live
sustainably on the planet without
creating you know ongoing damage to
natural systems and we found out the
Institute and then decided to be here to
find out so that's why and we moved
across the country to Cape Cod and
rented 12 acres of land and proceeded to
undertake really serious experiments in
food and energy
and I'm architecture looking for
alternatives and at what stage did you
really gain to the public recognition
and tranny essentially well early on and
it probably was a not a good thing in
the long run because we can probably got
the idea that anything we decided we
would do we could do quickly and easily
people started to we had barely planted
our first gardens before people started
to arrive in considerable numbers and
within a few years by the thousands
yeah-ah every week up to 10,000 visitors
um but there's a reason for it
we were we were even though we barely
had traction we were publishing a really
creative visions and designs and ideas
and telling the world this is what we're
going to do you know and it was kind of
bold we said we're going to restore the
lands protect the Seas and informally
it's - exactly - stories and and we
really went dead at it and I think one
of the advantages we had is both bill
and I were doom watch scientists so we
could see the unraveling of the natural
world through a very long telescope I
mean I had found that the social
communication signals and fishes could
be disrupted by agricultural chemicals
three and four orders of magnitude more
dilute than lethal levels - in essence
virtually eliminate them without killing
them and because the parents instead of
nurturing their young would eat the
young that's pretty
so we knew that the we had to go down at
this problems one thing that we did have
was the broad canvas roadmap
but Stuart brand was putting together
with the Whole Earth Catalog where he
set out you know as Diderot did in
France centuries earlier to sort of
reorganize knowledge around some kind of
new paradigm and the paradigm he chose
was the work of the systems thinker
Gregory Bateson and and and the work of
the arch designer
Buckminster Fuller and then he grafted
on that the sort of the wisdom and
Sensibility of people like Rachel Carson
that other people renting to those and
ready to both who were very very earth
in tune with the earth and its needs I
thought was it it was a it was a moment
who if you if you had to name three or
four or five people who really deeply
influenced your work in kind of them put
you on your way who would these people
be massive you start without certainly
Gregory Bateson certainly Stuart brand
William Irwin Thompson definitely
perhaps I'd put what anywhere when
Thompson first Margaret Mead
it's to a brand if I didn't say to a
break yeah well for me it was catalyzed
by some of the ecological writers and
thinkers and perhaps one of the most
profound was HT Odin when his in his
little book energy power and society he
said why don't we rethink life in such a
way that we can create a new partnership
and then he went on that make the
outrageous statements is that life forms
are just simply a vast bin of spare
parts for us to utilize in the creation
of ecological technologies that won't
harm the earth and I like that that had
a lot of had a lot of horsepower behind
it but we were also driven by a lot of
the social the social forces including
you know the brothers Goodwin in
communitas and and the writing itself no
I was talking about me and and principal
potkins
you know writing I had a lot of
fascination by that also the Joseph
Needham science and civilisation in
China was a big influence on me they're
just all over the place I was completely
omnivorous about about trying to
integrate knowledge and seeking sources
for him everywhere
I think Nancy's named the key players
and and then I've added this sort of the
the deep technological in the case of
Joseph Needham in scientific logical
case of Odum but there are many others
including my professors as a doctoral
student you yesterday you mentioned
Gregory Bateson referring to your work
as know there's an epistemology with the
future and we could you tell that story
again and also which particular bit of
the work was he was he referring to
I'll get Nancy to tell you the story but
basically I presented our work to a
Lindisfarne gathering at the very early
days of Linda's fire and Gregory was
there yes and interestingly John threat
directly followed after for Schumacher
so as one of our colleagues said John
set out like a golf ball on a tee
because Schumacher had a lot of the was
it Burma that he did a lot of his work
he had a lot of examples from elsewhere
but then John came on with slides at
that time not a PowerPoint and had
slides of everybody doing exactly what
at no alchemy
exactly what Fritz had said people
should do and so there we were you know
creating small healthy local economies
growing our own food looking for
alternative renewable energy sources
building windmills and obviously having
a good time and so when John finished
Gregory who's a great bear of a fellow
kind of turned it well now there's an
epistemology with a future we were
mighty pleased yes so that was it that
was that felt us if we'd ever had any
self doubt which he really didn't that
would have erased it that was just
wonderful well the reason why would not
have a ton of self-doubt is that our
work was really very romantic in the in
the in the aesthetic and cultural sense
you know we were you know sort of like
Gary Snyder's to be truly alive is to be
a transforming energies yeah yeah all
for a tremendous fun it's also stressful
but fun where did the tone
near Hulka me their eyes and could you
say a little bit more about why you
chose her
the it shows us it shows us yes it
really did we've been over anything all
kinds of things you know Oh sustainable
this and really quite boring non
memorable names and then one night time
remember so clearly John stuck his head
around the kitchen door we hadn't been
talking about anything it's not his head
around the kitchen door and said new
alchemy and I said yes it was just so
clear so was this idea yeah and it
worked and I it I know where the
Wellsprings came from it because our
knowledge of alchemy came later I was
looking at an arts Canada art magazine
and there were these little paintings on
stones that had been placed in I think
Vancouver Island and there was a little
caption saying modern day alchemy and
then months later this popped out of my
mouth and and it was maybe the two of
you and Velma clammy who was daunted yes
he also moved over from from California
to Reddington to Cape Cod yes and oh he
stayed for many many years well into the
80s yeah and he stayed as long as we did
what see his work in Costa Rica was new
alchemy in Costa Rica yeah and it's
called and I is still see a cylinder you
could probably say new alchemy bed and
weekend yeah yeah and and if he liked it
because serendipitously it also means
hope in the bri-bri native language so
so he he always saw himself as an
extension of
work oh yeah in in in Costa Rica and we
supplied him with lots of in terms and
talent that were nurtured here and then
went to help him there or spent you know
went for yeah that's a semester solo
spent on there it's a hugely successful
protective hugely successful what ifs of
the way and see such as at one of the
best months for development period a
tremendous amount of and the project on
Prince Edward Island also gave you a lot
of publicity how did that start it was
the UN year of habitat
Barbara Ward had announced some new
vision of human settlements at a UN
meeting in Vancouver British Columbia
and so the Canadian government was open
to new ideas for a short period of time
and so I approached Environment Canada
and after series and meetings proposals
the idea of an ark Prince Edward Island
was finally approved and and funded and
we started the designing and the track
and then most of us came from New
England to Prince Edward Island and then
of a group that worked on it the
majority stayed there to live the rest
of their lives and continued the work so
it was a it was a relatively short live
project probably no more than five years
but it incubated a whole new generation
of people in Canada they've done
remarkable work could you describe the
ideals to buy a shelter a little buy the
shelter is really the home for life
diverse life if you were to envision a
green house that was ecologically
designed in the sense that it was
protected from the north and open to the
south and received a lot of solar energy
but then your standard green house has
to use rather chemical management just
you know pesticides and that sort of
thing we never there were never any soap
it was a place to grow food and then
when we added ah in terms of vegetables
fruits and also raised fish and very
very a wonderfully fertile environment
that just cry mean we could ripen
tomatoes without any fossil fuel heat in
February in a well designed mean house
but the one in Prince Edward Island had
the added dimension is also a health sir
home so the with living quarters so that
is a whole new dimension of how to
supply sufficient energy from the wind
and the Sun to not only provide a void
space in a growing space but living
space it also had research space with
offices and computers and things like
that so it served a number of functions
I think the breakthrough with the bio
shelters was the proof that one could
take agricultural ecosystems and move
them indoors and allow them to
self-regulate in self design and protect
themselves from disease and pests and we
we assembled the ecology and it really
was a very collective effort no single
person knew exactly how to do it there
would be people working with IPM
integrated pest management other people
working with companion planting other
people working with one of my special
contributions was the creation of little
ecological islands what we call just
call refugia
we're beneficial organisms would be
present in the system but not the kind
of beneficial organisms that most
horticulturist think of they were things
like creatures like dragonflies and
damselflies that live in water so there
would be little pools amongst the things
so that was my personal contribution and
then there were others who looked at at
which kind of flowers had to be mixed
with the crops in order that the the
predatory insects would have a feet
source to feed on pests in other words
it was a really a superb example of
different kinds of intelligence working
in a given space to create a whole
system until the natural intelligence
including natural intelligence but what
is important I think that Jonathan made
the point that it was there well now
21st equivalent of a barn where you know
things were stored together out the cold
season and now with peak oil approaching
and climate change too could possibility
I think it's even more important because
people are going to need to produce much
more food locally and regionally and
this is a way of continuing to grow for
instance in an urban context you could
have one every few blocks or in every
neighborhood where people could have
year-round community gardens so they
have application I think even more now
and so much of what we were doing years
ago that's experimental is now becoming
a necessity so um the the time is caught
up with us and the early aquaculture
experiments with Makani and you growing
fish in these large large mats
eventually turned into productive living
machines and then at some point you also
decided to see if if these could be used
to clean up water could you just how
this kind of takes figure that will we
we
honored sunlight is a as a primary
organizing principle we created tanks
that had clear side so that in in three
dimensions sunlight can penetrate them
and and then we built ecosystems with
missions they built we assemble
ecosystems within them and then began to
create food chains that would produce
fish and as a byproduct of the
filtration of fish water also vegetables
and and greens and things like that so
again here is this process of of
capturing sunlight designing food webs
of trying to incorporate many of the
different kingdoms of life into a single
space so that they could integrate led
to first some theories about ecological
design which got published but a bit
later and and then move from food
production out into worrying about
problems of pollution and waste and
toxic environments and that led to
another level of of attempting to work
in an even more complex way with natural
systems and spent probably a decade
trying to figure out how to work with
toxic waste and sewage and septage and
industrial waste and so on and
eventually the the pieces began to fall
together so that by by getting on toward
the middle of the 1990s the theoretical
foundations for it had been laid out and
then after that period we then began to
look at how we can reassemble that
knowledge again and create what we call
agriculture
Etha parks so that you bring different
disparate activities together like
baking and brewing and sauce making and
restaurants and you combine those with
with new product development including
agricultural products and so there is a
continuum that began I would say with
some of McLaren East ponds and his
basement to the first solar ponds that I
created here all the way to where we're
at now which is more years later than
over 30 years and so now we're beginning
to think about even transforming
existing processes like sewage treatment
plants into sewage farms that will grow
higher plants botanicals that will
provide us with the biodiesel energy we
need in the future in other words why
throw away all the energy and nutrients
that's in human waste
why not redirect it into a pathway
that's applicable to a a era of possibly
scarce and scarce scarcities and
disruptions so there's a I think that
it's I can see a continuum and I've
never really written about it from my
first experiments at the Woods Hole
Oceanographic Institution where I tried
to create simulated tropical marine
environments in a greenhouse on Cape Cod
and began to develop for the first time
a science of ecological assembly in
other words where I took pieces and
elements from the edge of the sea and
put them in a greenhouse that I then was
able to create hold and fire
that allowed tropical fishes that I was
studying to actually breed in those
buildings and breeding marine fishes
it's not easy and it was just so
exciting to see this kind of assembly
and of course again all these influences
that were coming in at this time and
still are I was very impressed with levy
Strauss's book the raw and the cook and
the idea of the brechler
you know the enlightened tinkerer who
finds you know whatever it is around he
or she and to to create something
marvelous out of what most people would
see is junk and I thought that the same
kind of thinking could be applied to
living forms ecological elements this
for you to the birth of ecological
design and how would you define Inca
logical design for me it was and I was
slow to realize what I was doing but but
I had a sense of where I was headed well
as far as I'm concerned ecological
design is tapping into nature's
operating instructions and applying what
it knows and how it does things and in
what ways it accomplishes its ends which
are so much more efficient than anything
we can engineer on our own and also less
destructive and then direct it and this
is the design part directed towards
solving a human need whether its food or
fuels or environmental repair or waste
conversion or energy so are all of these
combined and you were both involved in
the adam joseph lewis and that
cool collaborative design were you not
just drunk yester in the collaborative
design process that created the building
could you say a little bit about that
process well I was I was certainly
present but I was a very minor actor on
the very exciting stage well though the
new alchemy ideas certainly worthy you
know yeah the original model that it's a
big battle shelter melee or arc and we
both went and spoken Overland and showed
a lot of flights yes so that into that
degree it expands to students yes
exactly and and and basically the David
or who is the impresario professor who
was the conductor of it all made some
very early on decisions which I think
made the project more exciting for some
of us at least and that was he intended
to include his students and the staff
and the faculty in the design so it was
a process that was not driven by the
experts you know the grand architect or
the brilliant engineer or the you know
the wicked ecological designer was all
done in a process and it was fascinating
to watch normally experts who are used
to telling people how to do things to
have to be part of a generative
collaborative process and that's that
was Davis genius and he had the patience
to put up with different people from
different directions at different speeds
coming into the process and I think
they're very few people at that time who
understood that collective design and
the stakeholder involvement in design
and I must say I've learned a lot about
it
in recent years but it really did come
out of a working with students on design
projects and working in that project
thing over them and you currently at the
University of Vermont and there's a
number of future visioning process is
going on there what's what's your vision
for the University of Vermont and also
for this newly to be established Journal
of ecological design well I have I've
looked at it in three ways first is the
idea of retrofitting badly designed
older buildings into very green
biologically friendly buildings which
we're trying to do at the Rubenstein
school for the environment Natural
Resources and that whole process of
reinventing what an existing building
could be is been just really remarkable
I can see I could see what it would be
like to walk through a ten years from
now I could I got I have it all on my
head thanks to a design process of kind
of just talked about the other thing is
that I would really like to see is if
the university is bold enough to go from
2006 December 2006 to June of 2022 and
transform itself into a carbon-neutral
institution
no longer dependent on fossil fuels for
its functioning and and to do so it
would also transform how universities
teach literacy including ecological
literacy and how they teach skills
universities tend to be clusters of
little silos with that with their own
with their own dimensions and rarely
cross the boundaries it's also very
important to a lot of its organic food
and locally produced food it's only just
beginning to penetrate the university
system I think Yale now has one of its
cafeterias or dining halls which is all
organic it's very very popular largely
the the students have been subsisting on
little better than junk food and it's
often rung by one of the big food
producing corporations and that is
gradually either they the food producing
corporations are starting to pay
attention to the need for local and
organic food but that's a high priority
as well and it's beginning to happen and
that too for the University of Vermont
seeing local food and Vermont is so
amazingly good at it and available
that's you've been a writer an editor
publisher for a long part of the but in
the last 35 years and he started off
with the Journal of the new alchemists
and then annals of Earth and you've both
written a number of books together you
recently published a book could you
could you say a little bit about your
career as a writer Ennis well first of
all impractically or practically it was
something I could do at home when my
children were small and I wanted not to
be away all the time when my kids were
little and secondly I'm not a scientist
so I really would didn't feel qualified
to do a lot of the work that was being
done both at Ocean arcs and at new
alchemy but I could write about it and I
figured by my writing about it I could
explain it in a way to people who also
weren't familiar with the science
because I wasn't you know how any
established group has its own sort of
language and way of communicating among
the members well seeing that really
wasn't a member of the scientific core I
could see the importance of what we were
doing and then try and make that
relevant to
a real leader who would be more in my
state of not really understanding I had
to struggle to learn to understand about
ecology and the interconnectedness of
everything and what didn't grow up
wasn't educated with those common
concepts at all but now they seem to me
it's obvious is breathing can you say
but what about how you put the
journalist in the alchemists together
and what tremendous plan first started
well what we did was um basically look
at everything that was going on at the
Institute in your range from gardening
composting tree planting fish raising of
course and many many different methods
of it uh and administration and then
people's other interests such as bill
McCartney and and Costa Rica and ask
everybody to make a contribution but
then if you just didn't both edit it but
organize it in a certain way it just
came out as a bunch of stuff you know
and there's so what I had to do was
organize it into sections and then after
that introduced the journal as a whole
and then introduced each article so that
people would see how they fit into the
whole and why this particular work was
even though they kept consisted of using
pond water to water vegetables to see
how that fit into the whole picture and
you recent book oh it's called safe and
sustainable world the promise of
ecological design the title was actually
the publishers I don't think I would
have been that without to us but they
assured me that you have such a short
time to catch this the attention of
somebody browsing in above the store
that you have to have a title or grab
them and it basically is tell
Ministry of both new alchemy and ocean
arts but because as I said earlier the
time is so right what we were doing then
was experimental and useful and
interesting but now most of those ideas
are a necessity we have to be able to
clean up our waste we have to learn how
to produce not food on the average
travels over a thousand miles to reach
people we peak oil with fossil fuel
prices rising we can't afford that we
can't afford it in terms of continuing
to transport things the way we do
because of climate change so all that
was ahead of its time is now practical
and realistic finally what's your vision
for the next 30 years in terms of what
needs to happen on a local regional
global scale in order for Humanity to
face that challenge that we have
transitioning into a sustainable human
civilization and are you hopeful or do
you think that we have to have an almost
collapse before we can rebuild or can we
change the system from within I think we
will anyway I think we're well on the
way there's been tremendous for instance
food I think it's a rallying cry but the
most obvious but also a lot of things
are happening in the area of getting off
fossil fuels but particularly with food
I mean the number of people who are
changing not only their eating habits
their buying habits the number of people
who are organizing for to really change
what people are called the food system
from the current industrial based one
the largest organization is called slow
food is global and it brings brings
together you know farmers from Kenya and
Rwanda with people from Bolivia Europe
North America and everybody is it's
somebody said oh it's generating a force
field one reporter put it around food
issues
and it's getting it has mainstream
writers involved so the books are
selling into the mainstream so I think
food is the most obvious one I think we
have to get out of fossil fuels period
as soon as possible
go carbon neutral I think we understand
enough in terms of the technology and
the knowledge to do it I really do and I
see what's dragoness ours is the
corporate nature of the global economy
and the indifference of a lot of the
people at the top to the changes that
have to happen because they're still
making money and that I think that is
too bottom-up movement and I think it's
well on its way and I think if you look
at the recent election in the United
States there are changes are well
underway I think the sort of oil
dominated our mentality has been death
of low and will continue to be double
how about you June
I don't know what percentage of the
culture is sleepwalking into the future
and don't foresee making major changes
or adjustments I really do believe that
Nancy's right in that there's a lot of
momentum being built up and it is it it
is true that people are are increasingly
becoming aware that something has to
happen
I think that Al Gore has done an
excellent job of conveying the need to
reduce the co2 and other greenhouse gas
emissions in the atmosphere if we're
gonna if we're gonna have a chance in
you know snowball's chance in hell of
getting through I'm fascinated by the
kind of counter-current response to this
with ingenuity beginning to pop up
everywhere and it really is a horse race
it's not clear whether we will avert a
crash there have been people saying that
you can't have a whole economic system
based on growth forever the planet can't
take it the system itself can't take it
the human beings can't take it so it
really is it really is anybody's guess
as to how the future is gonna turn out I
think what I tell students which is
which who our most important asset that
they
that they need to live as if they can
make a difference in the transformation
because anything less than that would
lead to despair and failure of this
human this human enterprise whatever one
calls it so on Mondays I'm optimistic
gun to cease I'm a pessimist em
Wednesdays I'm in despair and by
Thursday's and back being an optimist
again I'm a veritable roller coaster in
this department do you think that the
plan Journal of ecological design could
have a role in communicating a hopeful
vision helping people to see that this
transition is already happening
and I think the publication ecological
design if it formulates a to use Gregory
Bateson's phrase and epistemology with a
future and conveys it in enough
different ways then I think it could
have enormous influence I think it's
essential yeah I think it's essential if
it if it merely sets out to talk to
solely professionals and not
decision-makers and not people from
other sectors such as business or or
civic sectors it won't do it but if
somehow the the the ecological design
publications and I said that the pearl
because I don't think there's a single
way to communicate and you also agree
because otherwise you wouldn't have this
camera here right now
the it has an enormous possibilities for
and I like the idea that it it will be
multilingual even if only initially its
summaries but to to have a publication
in in you know Spanish French English
Mandarin it's kind of a kind of
interesting maybe Swahili you know could
be quite could be quite a force for good
thank you very much